Register of the Mikhail V. Alekseev Papers, 1905-1956
Hoover Institution Archives
Mikhail V. Alekseev Papers,
1905-1956
77066
Alekseev, Mikhail Vasil'evich, 1857-1918
1 manuscript box, 1 envelope (.5 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, writings, notes, memoranda, reports, military orders, and photographs, relating to Russian military activities during the Russo-Japanese War, World War I, and the Russian Civil War, and especially to the organization of the Dobrovol'cheskaia Armiia. Includes some posthumous biographical material
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1977.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Kornilov, Lavr Georgievich, 1870-1918; Nicholas II, Emperor of Russia, 1868-1918; Russia. Armiia--Officers; Russia (Territory under White armies, 1918-1920) Dobrovol'cheskaia armiia. Kornilovskii polk.; Russo-Japanese War, 1904-1905; World War, 1914-1918; World War, 1914-1918--Campaigns--Eastern; Russia; Soviet Union; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921
Biographical Note
1857 Born
1876 Graduated from the Moscow Military Cadet School
1877-78 Fought in the Turkish War
1904 Promoted to General
1904-05 Director of Operations of the II Army during the Russo-Japanese War
1912 Commander of the XII Army Corps
1914 Chief of Staff of the Southwestern Front in Galicia
1915 Commander-in-Chief of the Northwestern Front
1915-17 Chief of Staff for the Supreme Commander-in-Chief Nicholas II
1917 Military adviser to the Russian Provisional Government Organized the Volunteer Army
1918 Participated in the First Kuban Campaign (Icy March) Died, Ekaterinodar
Series Description
- Biographical File, 1918-1956 (Box 1.)
  Articles and notes relating to the life and military career of M. V. Alekseev. Arranged alphabeti-cally by author or title
- Speeches and Writings, 1916-18 (Box 1.)
  Manuscripts, reports and notes written by M. V. Alekseev. Arranged chronologically
- Correspondence, 1916-18 (Box 1.)
  Letters to and from M. V. Alekseev and other individuals. Arranged alphabetically by name of corres-pondent
- Subject File, 1905-1918 (Box 1.)
  Articles and reports. Arranged alphabetically by subject
- Photographs (10. A-V)
  See photo catalog for description
Container List
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1918-1956
  - Denikin, General Anton, memorandum on General Alekseev's death, September 25, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Kirilin, F., Osnovatel' i Vekhovnyi Rukovoditel' Dobrovol'cheskoi Armii General M. V. Alekseev, Rostov na Donu, 1919 (Folder 2)
  - Orlov, G., "General M. V. Alekseev - K Tridtsatipiatiletiiu Osnovaniia Dobrovol'cheskoi Armii," Bern, 1952 (Folder 3)
  - Untitled article in defense of General Alekseev and in response to a slanderous article published in Nasha Strana, No. 339, July 1956. In Russian. (Folder 4)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1916-18
  - "Tri Nedeli (22 avgusta - 14 sentiabria 1917)," n.d. Holograph (photocopy). (Folder 5)
  - "Dokladnaia Zapiska Generala Alekseeva Imperatoru Nikolaiu Vtoromu," June 25, 1916. Typewritten copy. (Folder 6)
  - Kornilov, Lavr, note concerning, September 1, 1917. Typewritten copy. In Russian. (Folder 7)
  - Summary of discussions with officers who arrived at the Don River for battle with the Bolsheviks, November 1917, Novocherkassk. Typewritten copy. In Russian. (Folder 8)
  - "Nekotorye Zametki i Pis'ma Posle Moego Otchisleniia ot Komandovaniia," 1918. Printed copy with photocopies of handwritten attachments. (Folder 9)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1916-18
  - Barther, General, 1917 (Folder 10)
  - Denikin, Anton, 1918 (Folder 11)
  - Denikin, Anton, letter to E. F. El'sner, 1918 (Folder 12)
  - Fedorov, Mikhail; Struve, Petr; Trubetskoi, Prince; 1918 (Folder 13)
  - Kornilov, Lavr, 1918 (Folder 14)
  - Lodyzhenskii, A. A., letter to Alexander F. Kerensky, 1917 (Folder 15)
  - Nicholas II, 1916 (Folder 16)
  - Voiskovoi Ataman, Novocherkassk, 1918 (Folder 17)
  - Voiskovoi Ataman Vsevelikogo Voiska Donskogo, 1918 (Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous, 1917 (Folder 19)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1905-1918
  - Russia - History - Revolution and Civil War
    - General (Folder 20)
    - Georgia, report on meeting with representatives of, September 12, 1918. In Russian. (Folder 21)
    - Moscow, military and political conditions, report on, by Colonel Novosil'tsev, June 1918. In Russian. (Folder 22)
    - War Minister Savinkov in Mogilev, August 24-25, 1917, and General Lavr Kornilov (Folder 23)
  - Russo-Japanese War, 1905-06 (Folder 24)
  - Stavropol', report on, n.d. In Russian. (Folder 25)
  - World War I, Russian military campaigns, 1915 (Folder 26)